<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Lord Lieutenant General of Ireland, for setling the Protestant religion, maintaining his Majesties just rights, and the priviledges of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1641-1649 : Ormonde)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E473_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203115</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863191</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863191</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90181)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E473[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Lord Lieutenant General of Ireland, for setling the Protestant religion, maintaining his Majesties just rights, and the priviledges of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1641-1649 : Ormonde)</author>
                  <author>Ormonde, James Butler, Duke of, 1610-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Cork, and re-printed at London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE Lord Lieutenant General OF <hi>IRELAND,</hi> For ſetling the Proteſtant Religion, maintaining his Majeſties Iuſt Rights, and the Priviledges of PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at Cork, and re-printed at London. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115377:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <head>BY THE LORD LIEVTENANT GENERALL OF <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>ORMOND,</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O prevent the too frequent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices incident through jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, diſtruſts, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtructions to all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, VVe account it not the leaſt worthy our labor up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inſtant of our Arrivall to prepare this people, whoſe welfare We contend for, with a right underſtanding of thoſe intentions in Us, which in Order to his Majeſties ſervice, We deſire may terminate in their good.</p>
            <p>To enumerate the ſeverall reaſons by which We were induced (for preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Engliſh intereſt) to leave the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and other his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Garriſons then under our power in this Kingdom, in the hands of thoſe intruſted by his two Houſes of Parliament, were to ſet forth a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115377:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->Narrative in place of a Manifeſt. It may ſuffice to be known, that thoſe Tranſactions had for one main ground this Confidence, That by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the power of the Houſes, they would upon a happy expected Compoſure of Affairs in England revert unto, and be reveſted in his Majeſty, as his proper right.</p>
            <p>But having found how contrary to the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the wel-affected to his Majeſties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration in England, the Power of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath unhappily devolved to hands im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed only in the Art and labour of pulling down, and ſubverting the fundamentals of Monarchy (with whom a pernitious Party in this Kingdome doe equally Sympathize &amp; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operate.) And being filled with a deepe ſence of the dutie and obligations that are upon Us ſtrictly to imbrace all opportunities of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our endavours towards the recovery of his Maieſties iuſt rights in any part of this Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Having obſerved the Proteſtant Army in the Province of Munſter (by ſpeciall providence diſcovering the Arts and practizes uſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle the members thereof, in ingagements as directly contrary to their duties towards God and man, as to their intentions and reſolutions) to have found means to manifeſt the Candor and Integrity thereof in a diſclaimer of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to, or concurrence with thoſe powers or perſons which have ſo groſly varyed even
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115377:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->their own profeſſed principles of preſerving his Majeſties Perſon and rights, by confining him under a moſt ſtrict Impriſonment, his Majeſty alſo vouchſafing graciouſly to accept the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſaid Army, as an eminent and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable expreſſion of their fidelity toward him, and in teſtimony thereof having laid his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands upon us, to make our repair unto this Province, to diſcharge the duties of our place.</p>
            <p>We have, as well in obedience there unto, as in purſuance of our own duty, and deſire to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Majeſties ſervice, reſolved to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence our approbation and eſteem of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the ſaid Army, by publiſhing unto the world our like determination in the ſame enſuing particulars, And accordingly We pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and declare,</p>
            <p>Firſt, to improve our utmoſt endeavours for the ſettlement of the Proteſtant Religion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of the beſt Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to defend the King in his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to maintain the Priviledges and Freedom of Parliament, and the Liberty of the Subjects, that in Order hereunto, We ſhall oppoſe to the hazard of our lives, thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels of this Kingdom who ſhall refuſe their Obedience to his Majeſtie, upon ſuch Terms as he hath thought fit by us to require it; And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115377:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->We ſhall indeavor to the utmoſt the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of that <hi>Independent</hi> Party, who have thus fiercely laboured the extirpation of the true Proteſtant Religion, the ruine of our Prince, the diſhonour of Parliament, and the Vaſſalage of our Fellow Subjects, againſt all thoſe who ſhall depend upon them, or adhere unto them: And that this our undertaking might not appear Obnoxious to the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> but that VVe deſire a firm Union and Agreement be preſerved betwixt us; We do likewiſe declare, that we will continue free Traffique and Commerce with all his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties good Subjects of <hi>England:</hi> And that We will not in the leaſt manner prejudice any of them that ſhall have recourſe to our Harbours, either in their bodies, ſhips, or goods, nor ſhall we take any thing from them without paiment of ready money for the ſame: And now that by his Majeſties ſaid Command, We have proceeded to re-enter upon the work of his ſervice in this Province, VVe conceive no higher Teſtimony can be given of his Majeſties acceptation, or of the eſtimation We bear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Us towards their Proceedings, then by reſorting unto them in perſon with His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Authority, and exhibiting unto them the incouragement and ſatisfaction they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in this aſſurance. That as We bear an eſpeciall regard to their preſent undertakings
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115377:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->and performances, accompanied with a reall Sence of their former ſufferings. So, leaſt there ſhould any advantage be derived unto thoſe who indeavor to improve all opportunities of ſowing ſedition and diſtruſt by this ſuggeſtion, that the former differences in judgement and opinion, which have induced perſons to ſerve diverſly under his Majeſty and the Parliament, will occaſion prejudice, or ill reſentments to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe towards ſuch perſons as have not former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concurred in Judgement with others in his Majeſties ſervice. We do delare, that We are qualified with ſpeciall Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from his Majeſtie, to aſſure them, that no diſtinction ſhall be made in any ſuch Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, but that all perſons now intereſted and engaged in this Cauſe, ſhall be reflected upon with equall fervour and regard; And that We ſhall make it our indeavours ſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and confirm his Majeſties Gracious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure towards them, as that we will never call to memory any paſt difference in Opinion, Judgement, Action, or Profeſſion, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of any Member of this Army, or any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon relating to it, but on the contrary, ſhall be very ready to atteſt our good Affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in the diſcharge of ſuch good Offices as ſhall be in our power. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn whereof, We ſhall only expect their perſeverance in their preſent engagements for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115377:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->his Majeſties ſervice with ſuch alacrity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and affection, as may ſuit with their late publike declaration, and profeſſions. To whom We deſire this aſſurance alſo may be inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. That as We ſhall in the future uſe our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt care &amp; diligence to provide for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from the like hardſhips, to thoſe they have formerly undergone; ſo We have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy imployed our beſt induſtry and endeavours for the ſettlement of ſuch a courſe as we may (with moſt reaſon) hope will in theſe uncertain times produce a conſtant, and competent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance for them, enabling them to make ſuch a progreſſe in their preſent undertakings, as may, with the accompliſhment of the great ends thereof, eſtabliſh their own Honour and Content. Thus much we have thought fit to publiſh to the world, to furniſh it with an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſtrong conviction againſt Us, if We ever ſwerve (to the beſt of our power) from the juſt wayes of maintaining the true Proteſtant Religion, the Honour and Intereſt of his ſacred Majeſty, the juſt Rights of Parliament, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subjects, and the ſafety, quiet, and welfare of the people intruſted to our care.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
